<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caueat for cold Christians. In a sermon preached by Mr. Paul Bayne ... Wherein the common disease of Christians, with the remedie, is plainly and excellently set downe for all that will vse it</title>
            <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05967</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836942</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836942</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05967)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 950:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caueat for cold Christians. In a sermon preached by Mr. Paul Bayne ... Wherein the common disease of Christians, with the remedie, is plainly and excellently set downe for all that will vse it</title>
                  <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>pImrinted by Felix Kyngston, for Nathanael Newbery, and are to be sold at his shop vnder St. Peters Church in Cornhill, and in Popes-head Alley, right against the signe of the white horse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CAVEAT FOR COLD CHRISTIANS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN</hi> A SERMON PREACHED BY M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PAVL BAYNE, SOMTIMES Miniſter of Gods Word at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes, in Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN THE COMMON DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of Chriſtians, with the remedie, is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and excellently ſet downe for all that will vſe it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn 15.9.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Continue ye in my loue. If ye keepe my Commandements, ye ſhall abide in my loue.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornhill, and in Popes-head Alley, right againſt the ſigne of the white horſe. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1240:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1240:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL, HIS SIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GVLAR GOOD FRIEND, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ROBERT CLAVERING, Towne-Clarke of Newcaſtle, all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of a better life, and this preſent.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, conſidering the good accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that ſome former few Sermons of that religiouſly-learned, and learnedly-religious Diuine, Maſter <hi>Paul Bayne</hi> haue had with the Church of God, the enſuing Sermon lying hitherto by me, I was (without difficulty) induced to make it publike. For if I ſhould longer conceale it, what know I whether ſome body elſe, who had not the like interest to it that my ſelfe haue, might not preuent me in printing this, as well as they haue done in publiſhing ſome other things of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Moreouer, looking into the carriage and frame of this draught, I did not ſee how it could diſparage any of the rest, which are flowne abroad before it. Laſtly, if we will ponder the ſubiect matter diſcourſed of in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing leaues, I will permit it to any indifferent wiſe-hearted Christian Reader, who vieweth the estate of the
<pb facs="tcp:1240:3"/>times, and waigheth aduiſedly what ſingular vice raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; what eſpeciall graces are ordinarily defectiue among Profeſſors, whether this Sermon vttereth not<note n="*" place="margin">Commoda accommoda.</note> profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table things, and profitable things in their ſeaſon. For when (reſpected Sir) did the like wofull declining from the ancient feruor of our first loue, ſo generally ſpread it ſelfe through all the quarters of our Iland? He hath but halfe an eye, who looking vp and downe, beholdeth not, that euery little nothing in zealous forwardneſſe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, ſeemeth (for the most part) very ſufficient. We will neither diligently prouoke our ſelues to liuely procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in the way of powerfull walking with God; neither will we patiently endure others to outſtrip vs, and to aſpire vnweariedly after the highest pitch of well doing. This leauing our firſt loue, this abatement of former light and heate in our Christian courſe, is proued in the enſuing Sermon, and reproued. When was there ſo little minding and remembring whence we are (generally) not ſlidden, but (as it were) fallen headlong? When were there ſo few ſincere and ſetled reſolutions, to repent of the euill of relinquiſhing our firſt loue, a ſinne wherein our land hath ſinned, beſides all its other ſinnes? Alas, the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied employment of our memories, to conſider whence we are fallen; ſhame and confuſion of face working true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that we are ſo fowlie fallen; are ſtrange things vnto vs! although onely the exerciſe of theſe graces can raiſe vs vp to true happineſſe in this life, and in the next. That we may ſet vpon theſe ſauing practiſes, wee are effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually called vpon in the fore-named Sermon. So that (as I formerly ſaid) it will (I perſwade my ſelfe) proue both profitable and ſeaſonable to the Chriſtian Reader; who hath a diſcerning ſpirit, both what his owne wants are, and how, by this little booke, ſome pretty ſupply may
<pb facs="tcp:1240:3"/>be affoorded him for his recouering.</p>
            <p>Thus much why the Sermon is publiſhed: a word or two (Worthy Sir) why, by a more eſpeciall inſcription, I haue dedicated it to your name. Firſt (therefore) I was moued hereto with an earnest deſire, to manifeſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then euer yet I haue done, the entireneſſe of my dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt affections toward you; who after our many yeeres comfortable louing and liuing together, of late haue been remoued from me into thoſe Northerne parts. Not being therefore now able face to face to enioy the wonted ſweet intercourſe of ſpeech, and other friendlike offices, I longed (notwithſtanding) to tell you, you were not ſo much out of mind, as out of ſight. Secondly, I deſired that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication might befit the perſon, remembring <hi>Senecaes</hi> counſell:<note n="*" place="margin">Vtique caue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus, ne mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſuperuacua mittamus: vt foeminae aut ſeni arma venatoria, aut ruſtico li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros, aut ſtudijs ac literis dedito retia. <hi>Sen. de ben. l. 1. cap. 11.</hi>
               </note> we muſt take heede wee ſend not ſuperfluous gifts, as to a woman or old man hunting weapons; or to a clowne, bookes; or nets to one following his ſtudies, and learning. On the contrary, to ſend a booke to a ſcholer; or a Sermon, to an experienced profeſſor, I cannot ſee but it will hold good proportion.</p>
            <p>Thus not doubting, but you will louingly receiue what was louingly intended, I take my leaue; deſiring that hee who hath begun the good worke ſome yeeres agoe in you, and hath made you graciouſly proceed hitherto; euen hee (the mercifull and true God) would perfectly accompliſh it, vnto the day of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the ſureſt bond,</hi> EZ. Ch.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>1618.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1240:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1240:4"/>
            <head>A CAVEAT FOR COLD CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIANS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. 2.4.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Neuertheleſſe I haue ſomewhat againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt loue: remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe thy first workes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S a husband abſent aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his wife by letter, of that which is behoouefull; ſo it pleaſeth our Sauiour Chriſt, abſent in body, though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in ſpirit, to admoniſh his Spouſe, and this Church in particular, by an Epiſtle ſent to her. In it we may obſerue theſe three parts:<note place="margin">Three parts in the Epiſtle. <hi>1.</hi> The preface.</note> firſt, the preface, containing the perſons written vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and writing; the one wee endorſe on the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of our letters; the other we vſe to ſubſcribe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them. Secondly, the matter;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> The matter, in which are three things.</note> in which three things are contained: firſt, becauſe loue edifieth, he beares her witneſſe of the things commendable in her; that his rebuke, comming from loue, might be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1240:5"/>better digeſted. Secondly, in this 4. verſe he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth that, for which he had a ſaying to her, that is to ſay, that ſhe was fallen from her firſt loue, it was decayed in her. Thirdly, in the fifth and ſixth verſes hee preſcribes a remedy: in ſetting downe which, he obſerues this order: firſt, he ſets downe a double practice which would reſtore her, <hi>viZ.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring her fall and repenting. Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the medicine is bitter, and not eaſily taken; hee ſhewes her the great perill, the mortall hurt which will enſue, if this be neglected. Thirdly, hee encourageth his patient; ſhewing, that yet there was a good ſigne, that loue was not quite gone, though it was in ſome ſort leſſened and enfeebled, becauſe ſhe hated the workes of the Nicolaitans: Thus with a bitter potion, ſending her a <hi>manus Chriſti;</hi> Chriſt folding vp (as it were) a pill in gold, that it might bee let downe the more pleaſantly. Hauing finiſhed the matter, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſion. </seg>3</label> he comes to conclude: in which, firſt by a ſolemne <hi>O yes,</hi> hee makes attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and for a cloſe, makes a moſt comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſuch who ſhould ouercome, outwreſtling by repentance ſuch tentation, as accompanies theſe declinings, <hi>viz.</hi> that they ſhould haue further reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Chriſt made in them, and further commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for the preſent by grace with him; and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the bleſſed fruition of him in glory.<note place="margin">The ſumme of the words.</note> The ſumme of theſe words to be handled is this: though many good things be found with thee, yet thy firſt loue is left; the flame of thy loue which reached to heauen, waſted all inordinate concupiſcence, and was fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in good workes, this is ſunke downe and quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; therefore aduiſe with thy ſelfe, and well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1240:5"/>how thou art fallen (as it were) from heauen to earth; iudge this thine owne iniquitie; turning from it, returne to God in the waies of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, bringing forth the ſame fruits of liuely loue, which heretofore haue been diſcerned in thee. Thus we may fitly come to the conſiderations, which may directly be deduced from theſe words for our further inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeru. </seg>1</label> 
               <note place="margin">The diſeaſe.</note> that theſe Epheſians are chalenged to haue left their firſt loue, wee ſee what is the condition of Chriſtians; come to ſome good ſtate, they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to decline; when now they haue made great proceeding in loue, they are ready to coole againe. Euen as it is in the body, when it is in the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent temperature, the durance thereof is not long; ſo it is in the ſoule alſo, when it is in the beſt taking, euen then it is ſubiect to alteration. So the Galathians, the Iſraelites; how ſoone did the one fall from the Goſpell, and the other from their ioy in that God, which had deliuered them? Such is our frailty, and ſuch are Satans enterpriſes againſt vs. But for more full opening of this point,<note place="margin">The firſt opened.</note> two things ſhall be vnfolded; firſt, what it is the true Chriſtians fall from, when they leaue their loue: 2. whence it comes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> being ſo wel proceeded they decline. To the firſt let, that it is not the tranſitorie flaſhing, the ſweetneſſe, the delight, or gladneſſe in heart which wee feele in our firſt loue. For this which comes not ſo much from the things of our peace, as from the nouelty of them; from this, that the light of them doth firſt ſhine vnto vs; this which by reaſon of ſuch circumſtance is in vs, may bee loſt and left without ſinne: the Angels loue workes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1240:6"/>ſomewhat in them touching the conuerſion of a ſinner, when now he is firſt conuerted, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly abides not with them: as for example, the ioy there mentioned, Luk. 15. Secondly, I ſay it was not that diuine quality of loue, which the ſpirit of God bringeth forth in regenerating of vs; for this could not bee loſt, it being part of our new birth which abideth; according to that, Hee who is borne of God ſinneth not, for the ſeede of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth him: and Cor. 1.13, Loue faileth not; not onely becauſe for the kind it abides in heauen, but becauſe the ſelfe ſame in number, which by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is brought forth in vs, ſhall neuer haue end; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a diuine fier, which no waters of tentation can quench and extinguiſh. It remaines then, that they are ſaid to haue left their firſt loue, in regard that their outward works (which are as conſpicuous fruits growing out of this tree of loue), in regard, I ſay, that theſe were decayed and impaired, they are ſaid to haue left their firſt loue. Theſe are all of them things ſubiect to alteration: though the diuine qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Chriſt remaine with vs; the Scripture makes this, to be rooted in loue, a diſtinct thing from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing loue. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore asking in the third of the Epheſians, in behalfe of them, that they might bee rooted in loue, and ſo made able to apprehend more perfectly the loue of God to them in Chriſt, aimes at ſome ſingular degree of affection. For as plants are not (when preſently ſet firſt) deeply roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: ſo theſe diuine graces, faith, loue, &amp;c, grow vp in vs to ſuch a rooted firmeneſſe, and ſetledneſſe, that wee are not eaſily moued and troubled in the practice of them. A man loues truly at firſt, yet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1240:6"/>leſſe groundedly. Whence it is, that little entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments allure him, and withdraw him into naps of ſpirituall forgetfulneſſe; little ſnibs diſmay him, and make him ſhrinke in; little things make him doubt of Gods loue to him; yea, of his owne perſeuering in loue to God: but being better acquainted by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience with the Lords fidelity, mercy, patience, &amp;c, he takes rooting more and more in this holy affection. Now it is ſo, that the loue of theſe Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians began to hang more looſe in them, then ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it was wont. For looke as any thing that now ſtands ſtedy, may come to bee looſened, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine the thing it was before, though not firme as before; ſo it is in loue: ſo ioynts that are looſened, yet remaine ioynts. Secondly, the operation, the feruent mouing of loue was growne remiſſe. For looke as in materiall fiers, the feruent heate may ſlake, and fier ſtill abide; as in the body, the powers of hearing and ſeeing are ſafe (as in ſleepe), though the exerciſe of them bee ceaſed and bound for a time: euen ſo our loue, which (like a fier) groweth further and further kindled in vs for a time, may be by ſome occaſions abated, in regard of the feruor and heate, when yet the being of it is ſtill continued. Thirdly, in regard of works, which the operation of their loue produced in their ſoules in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and toward God and man outwardly, in this regard they were declined. In their ſoules, the light of the Lord did not diſcuſſe the clouds of ſelfe and earthly luſtings, as it had done formerly; nor were their duties ſuch now, as ſometime they had been toward God and man. Looke as in the Sunne, the eſſentiall brightnes remaining the ſame,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1240:7"/>the effect neuertheleſſe of it in diſperſing clouds, and in lightening the ayre is ſomtime diminiſhed, ſometime quite eclipſed: ſo here the diuine nature or light of loue remaining, yet the effect thereof in their ſoules, both in clearing them from earthly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, &amp; falſe loues; as alſo in making them fruitfull in good duties, this effect of it was nothing for meaſure, ſuch as once might haue been obſerued in them. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Now if you aske, whence it comes to paſſe, that a man hauing made good proceedings, ſhould decay in his loue; I anſwere: Firſt, from a ſecret ſloth, which makes vs wearie of well doing. A dull Aſſes trot will not laſt long: ſuch wee are of our ſelues, there being a ſpirituall ſluggiſhneſſe hanging about our bones, which is ſtill ready to returne on vs. For this it is that the Scripture calleth on vs, Bee not ſlothfull, Hebr. 6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the longer wee are oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in any thing, the more wee are taken with a ſatiety of it. This we ſee proues true euen in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of nature; no wonder then if Manna grow no meate with vs, if heauenly things and courſes ſeeme leſſe taſtfull, while they are continued; eſpecially while we neglect to take paines with our hearts, that we may come to the thankful vnderſtanding of ſo great benefits; and on the other ſide, to the prudent obſeruation of our wants; whether wee looke at the inward frame of our ſoules, or at any dutie which we performe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we ſee that the more we goe to the perfection of any thing, the more difficulty we finde: now when wee come to meet with hardneſſe, there wee are ready (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtrength miniſtred) to ſlack our endeauour, and thinke with the ſluggard, Better an handfull with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1240:7"/>eaſe, then farre more with diſquietneſſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, the diuell, by ſinnes of time and perſons among whom we liue, much weakens our loue; through the abundance of iniquitie loue ſhall waxe cold. Sometime the example of others (like a backe-byas) drawing vs from the preciſeneſſe of our care in ſome duties, in which wee endeauoured before to walke with God: otherwiſe the ſcoffing, and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſpightfulneſſe of wicked ones, making vs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſhew our loue as we would and ſhould with liberty beſeeming. Euen as a damp puts out a light: ſo this fog of ſin ſuffocates and ſmothers the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome blaze of loue, though it cannot quench it throughout in vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, the diuell commonly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens vpon vs a ſpirituall ſecurity and fulneſſe, when we are ſomewhat proceeded (whereas wee ſhould forget what is paſſed); and being ſecure and full, we watch leſſe againſt ſuch things, as by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle quench the ſpirit in vs. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Now ſeeing this is the condition of Chriſtians in good eſtate, it muſt bee as a glaſſe to vs, wherein we may behold our frailty. Did theſe, when now they were gone on farre in grace, did they then giue in and decline? though it be the ſtate of ſome onely, yet it muſt breed a holy terrour in vs all, making vs liſten to the counſell, Let him that ſtands, take heed leſt he fall. Eſpecially, we muſt be carefull, becauſe wee liue in the laſt times, wherein this cold fit growes a popular diſeaſe: the loue of many ſhall waxe cold through abundance of iniquity. Now as liuing where ſome bodily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious diſeaſe raigneth, we will looke to our ſelues more carefully: ſo we muſt proportionably bee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect for our ſoules, that they bee not infected
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1240:8"/>by this common contagion. Some thinke that when we teach, that true loue, where it is once, there it is euer, and ſo of true grace; there is opened a window to ſecurity, and we make men warrants to liue as they liſt: but there is no ſuch matter, while we teach that they may fall into ſuch languiſhing ſickneſſes, as will make their conditions ſeeme a liuing death, rather then otherwiſe. Were the conditions of our bodies immortal, yet ſuch, as on any miſ-diet might contract painfull and fearfull ſickneſſes; ſhould wee then haue cauſe to be ſecure, &amp; caſt away all care of dieting our ſelues? ſo it is in our ſoules; though this life of loue is eternall, yet it is ſubiect to ſuch lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing maladies without the greater care taken, that none of vs in this reſpect can want a ſufficient ſpurre to incite our diligence. I will deferre a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word of exhortation to the next inſtruction. Marke then as theſe fell away in their loue, ſo the Lord challenges them for it, as a thing much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing his Maieſty, and dangerous to their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Obſerue hence, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeru. </seg>2</label> that coldneſſe and remiſneſſe in the courſes of ſuch as are religious, much offend God. God accurſeth ſuch as doe his worke ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, though he bid them ſheath their ſwords in the blood of others: and the luke-warme Chriſtian, that is neither hot nor cold, the Lords ſtomacke beares not. To lend the clearer light to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, we muſt firſt know what this ſinfull remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is: ſecondly, why it is ſo diſpleaſing and harmefull. For the firſt, a man is not to thinke all that a remiſſe courſe (here challenged), which comes ſhort of ſome more powerfull and fruitfull ſtraine in his courſe of life, which he hath paſſed. For there
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1240:8"/>are degrees of diligence, and the leaſt well accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with God. Euen as an induſtrious husband hath ſome ſeaſons, wherein his labour is double to that it is ordinarily, and yet his courſe is at no time idle: ſo a ſpirituall good husband, may (on occaſions) be lifted to ſuch powerfull endeauour, which he hath not continuing with him at all times, and yet be farre from this ſinfull remiſneſſe. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is not a remiſſe, feeble, weake walking, which proceedeth from a ſpirituall faintneſſe in vs, being vnder many tentations; for euen feeble and remiſſe actions in this ſeaſon, are no ſmall labour of our loue, and moſt acceptable to God; we muſt not goe all by quantity. A ſicke man may ſhew more labour, and tire his feebled ſtrength more, in doing that which in two houres might bee diſpatched, then a ſound man can ſhew in a whole dayes worke. For though the ſound man doth more in quantity, yet he doth leſſe in proportion then the ſicke, ſo farre the ſicke is from being idle. Euen as the rich men that offered, though they gaue more in quantitie then the widow; yet ſhe did more in proportion (if her ability be conſidered) then they all. It therefore not being a comparatiue remiſneſſe, which may be ſo termed, in regard of more extraordinary beſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſelues, nor yet a feeble remiſneſſe; what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, but that it ſhould bee ſuch a remiſneſſe, as commeth from ſpirituall ſloth, cauſed in vs by luſts, which we haue in ſome degree entertained? Forwhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> luſts do get the vpper hand ſo ouer vs, that we ſtriue not with them, but goe on in them, though they eat out the life and power which we felt in our courſes, and make vs that we can be well enough, though we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1240:9"/>feele not our communion with God in that meaſure we were wont; this is euer ioyned with a ſinfull fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the loue in which we walked.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſon wherein this comes to be ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> is taken from Gods coniugall loue, which makes him holily iealous of the loue of his people. What doth a louing husband take ſo grieuouſly as the finding want of loue in his ſpouſe; as to ſpie the hart of her withdrawne, that it is not as it was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore toward him? and it is harmfull to vs, by cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſometime outward chaſtiſement (as ſloth in ſcholers &amp; ſeruants, forceth correction from gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors), by cauſing vnceſſantly a waſting of the life of grace in vs. For as fier not blowne, goes out; ſo this loue, when we are growne cold and remiſſe, dies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, &amp; fals into a dangerous ſwoune, which makes our ſtates not a little frightfull.</p>
            <p>This then being a thing ſo diſpleaſing and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> we muſt examine our ſelues how it is with vs, whether we haue not taken ſome ſpice of this cold. If wee would apply our conſideration nationally, what doth the Atheiſme, the meere brood of Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the ſwarming of Papiſts, the drunkenneſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes of theſe time proclaime, but that our loue is in ſome meaſure left? But wee will ſtraine this ſtring no further, becauſe it is the beſt for vs to weare our eyes at home; if wee looke to our ſelues perſonally, ſhall we finde it otherwiſe? Cannot wee many of vs take pleaſure in the company of ſuch, who care not how they prouoke our heauenly huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? doe not we walke without feeling, feare of offending our God? cannot we paſſe ouer our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences lightly, caſting that at our heeles, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1240:9"/>grieues his heart? cannot we ſlight ouer our duties, and put God off with ſuch ſorrie ſeruice, as if any thing were good enough for him? haue we not had ſometime good purpoſes and endeauours, from which now we are fallen? If wee be priuie to theſe things, it is too ſure, our firſt loue is exceedingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, we muſt awaken our hearts, and ſtirre them vp to this loue. Let vs thinke, Lord, ſhould I offer this meaſure to an earthly husband, neuer to bee afraid after doing that, which I knew would diſpleaſe him; to take delight inſuch (I knew) neuer bare him good will; would it not make me bluſh? how much leſſe ought I to vſe thy Maieſty ſo iniuriouſly? We brooke not, that loue ſhould not grow in them toward vs, with whom we are married; why ſhould our loue be leſſened to thee? We would checke our ſelues in affoording vnchaſt fauours to men; what cauſe haue we to take vp our ſelues, that our affections giue ſuch vnchaſt kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to theſe earthly delights; and dwell ſo in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace of them, that they are indiſpoſed, &amp; wanting deuotion toward thy Maieſty? O let vs take words to our ſelues and blow this ſparke, that it may flame vpward toward our God. If while our hearts are in the loue of ſome louely creature, we finde ſuch ſweetneſſe; what a heauen ſhould they feele, did they loue the Lord affectionately? in this loue there would be no lacke.</p>
            <p>Againe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> while we haue not ſome warmth of loue in our courſes, nought we do is accepted. If I would giue my body to be burned, and wanted loue (ſaith the Apoſtle), it profited nothing. Euen as no office
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1240:10"/>is acceptable to a husband from a wife, when the loue of her heart is withdrawne and cooled. On the contrary, it ſhould prouoke vs to renue our loue, becauſe while this is liuely in vs, God ſees many faults, and ſees them not: as in <hi>Dauid,</hi> whom God counted after his heart, but in the matter of <hi>Vriah.</hi> It is plaine, that God did not looke at any infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, while his ſeruant (in this maine matter of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual loue) kept vpright with him. Looke as it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene husband and wife, while loue and fidelity are kept inuiolable, little faults are not obſerued and ſtood vpon ſo, as to make falling out betwixt them; ſo it is twixt God and his people: while this heate of loue is ſtirred vp in our courſes, our ſoules ſhall be preſerued in healthſome ſtate, and grace en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. For as that exerciſe, which doth ſtirre vp the naturall heate, if it be but <hi>ad ruborem vſque,</hi> doth benefit the body, waſting (in ſome degree) the ſuperfluities, which are ready to breed enſuing ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: So not onely thoſe eminent mouings of loue, wherein ſhee exceedes her ſelfe; but euery courſe which is with life and power of loue in any meaſure, encreaſeth and ſtabliſheth grace, and conſumes the reliques of corruption in vs.</p>
            <p>Finally, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> if nothing will moue vs to weane our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and ſet them more feruently on the Lord; but that we will goe on key-cold (in a manner) to God-ward: then the Lord will not faile to pay vs home with our owne coyne; and make theſe things breed vs ſmart, which wee haue moſt inordinately loued, to his great diſhonour.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing conſidered the diſeaſe,<note place="margin">The remedy.</note> we come to the remedie, which ſtands in a double practice: the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1240:10"/>one preparatiue to the other; the one of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring whence ſhe was fallen; the other of repenting, which is ſet forth by the fruit of it, <hi>Repent and doe thy firſt workes.</hi> In the firſt we are to marke two things; firſt, the action commanded, <hi>Remember.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the obiect of it, <hi>whence thou art fallen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence wee obſerue, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeru. </seg>3</label> with what our memories are to be taken vp; euen with our eſtates, and the declinings of them.</p>
            <p>For opening this doctrine, two things muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on. Firſt, we muſt open what remembrance is, what it containeth within the compaſſe of it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, what is to be remembred of vs. For the firſt, as we ſee it is with man, hee hath ſome worke without doores, vvhich he goes out to; ſome he doth, ſtaying vvithin: ſo the mind doth ſome things vvithout, ſome things it doth retired into it ſelfe, keeping vvithin it ſelf, and vvorking onely on it ſelfe; as when it remembers or deliberates on any matter. Novv euery vvorking of the mind, tends either to this end, that vve may knovv better by meanes of it; or that vve might doe ſomthing that is behoouefull. Novv this remembrance is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine operation of the ſoule vvithin it ſelfe, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vve thinke on things forgotten; to the end vve may be ſtirred vp to ſuch conſcionable practice, as the nature of the thing remembred requires. It containes three things; firſt, an entring into our ſelues; vvhen a man returneth into his thoughts, no longer vvandring to and fro in theſe outvvard things, in vvhich he had (after a ſort) loſt and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten himſelfe: For this is the beginning of that remembrance vvhich leades to repentance; See
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1240:11"/>Deut. 30.1. 1. King. 8.47. Secondly, a bethinking and calling things to mind ſo farre, as to know how things ſtand with vs. Thirdly, when we are bid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, we are enioyned to ſet our hearts on, keepe in mind, conſider the ſtate we are in, and conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it, Pſal. 50.22, <hi>Conſider this ye that forget God.</hi> Where conſideration and forgetfulneſſe are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>I conſidered my wayes, and ſo repented.</hi> Thus you ſee, what this duty of remembrance includes in it.</p>
            <p>Now for the matter to be remembred, it is our eſtate, and the declining of it.</p>
            <p>For next to God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> we are to haue our owne eſtates in mind; both what they were before grace, Eph. 2. for it doth make vs thankfull, diligent, humble: we muſt not, with the Prieſt, forget our old Clerk-ſhip; we muſt ſtill carrie in mind our naturall eſtate, to the ends aboue named.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> we muſt remember our eſtates ſince grace; both in regard of our frailty and proneneſſe to fall, though we ſtand through Gods protection and ſupportance: for this will make vs meeke to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Galath. 6.1, and watchfull ouer our ſelues. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in regard of our falles ſince we receiued grace; whether they be ſuch, of which we hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, find them already pardoned, Deut. 9.7; or whether they be ſuch falles, in which wee haue lien hitherto durtily, not awaking our ſelues to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And this laſt remembrance is required of theſe Epheſians, that they ſhould remember and conſider how much they were declined, though they little tooke it to heart. For this duty is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that we may feele in our ſelues a ſpurre to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, in which the face is writhen awry ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1240:11"/>The ſight of our naturall deformity in a glaſſe, ſtirs vp nature to inforce her ſelfe to remoue it: ſo here the looking wiſhly on our ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, excites euen feeble grace to doe her vtmoſt endeauour for correcting it.</p>
            <p>This which hath been ſpoken, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> ſerues to conuince many, who liue neuer once retuning to their harts, and conſidering their ſtate in ſuch wiſe, as might make them wiſe to ſaluation. Many goe like hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed haukes, neuer once thinking on that which hurts them, till their ſoules are ready to fly from their bodies, and their condition helpleſſe. For partly the ſoule (as it is ſaid of the harlot, whoſe feet keepe not at home) the ſoule (I ſay) liues in the ſenſes more then in it ſelfe: as an vnchaſt mans heart is more with his miſtriſſe, then at home with himſelfe: ſo our ſoules wedded inordinately to this fleſh, are more occupied about theſe ſenſible things, and dwell more in them then in themſelues. Againe, Satan is moſt malitious to hold vs chat (as it were), and keepe vs occupied till this time and ride of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation be ouerſlipped: and finally, the exerciſe ſo little ſutes to an impenitent heart (for men that are bankrupts, what pleaſure take they in reuiewing their bookes?), that almoſt none entring into him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, calles to mind and fixedly holds his heart to thinke on things of this nature. This neglect (like a flood-gate opened) letteth in all euill and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency. What makes men ſweare, bowze, giue place to their luſts, goe on in hardneſſe of heart? is it not that they are ignorant, or that they haue an erroneous iudgement, as if theſe were lawfull, and repentance needleſſe? it is forgetting themſelues,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1240:12"/>and neuer once conſidering what they doe, and how they goe on. Secondly, we muſt make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to exerciſe our remembrance about this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, euen what ſweruings and declinings haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken vs. In our bodies and eſtates we will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marke what is amiſſe, and not eaſily forget it: If matter of wrong be done to vs, it ſtickes in memory, as if it were written in braſſe: we are not weary of remembring earthly things, ſuch is our eſtimation of them, and familiar acquaintance with them. Shal we onely be wanting to our ſelues in remembring here, when our ſaluation lieth vpon it? therefore as you will haue the latter end peace, ſo remember your wayes, ſinnes, declinings; the more you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them, the more God will forget them (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably to that, If we condemne our ſelues, God will not condemne vs), and we had need hold our hearts to the remembrance of them; they will not heare lightly on this ſide. Such is the loue in vs to our naturall good, and care to auoid ſickneſſe, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty; that we cannot ſo ſoone call to mind our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and dangers, but that we apprehend them, and turne from them. But ſo auerſe are we from our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly good, and careleſſe of ſpirituall dangers; that when we ſpeake of them againe and againe within our ſelues, the ſoule will hardly be mooued to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the one, or giue attendance to the other ſo, as to ſeeke the auoidance of them. Alas, if we will not now be brought to thinke of our daily ſlips, decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, of the grieuous ſinnes in which we goe on without repentance; if we will not, I ſay, God ſhall one day enlarge our memories, that they ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all our ſinnes: yea this hardneſſe of heart,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1240:12"/>which would not let them repent, when exhorted; and that in ſuch ſort, that the remorſe and after-thought of them ſhall be as a worme that neuer dies. He who doth moſt willingly forget his ſinnes here, ſhall remember them there, moſt fully and painfully hereafter.</p>
            <p>To proceed to the ſecond practice, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeru. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Remember whence thou art fallen, and repent.</hi> Firſt marke, vpon the declinings of grace he bids them repent; teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the leaſt declinings of grace in our ſelues and others, is a cauſe of repentance.</p>
            <p>The falles of others we muſt repent of, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> leſt we make them ours, &amp; inwrap our ſelues in their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. We are members of the ſame body with them; and therefore what we doe in our owne, we muſt in ſome proportion doe in their ſinnes alſo. When the health of body declined in <hi>Dauids</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit friends, he humbled himſelfe in faſting, Pſal. 35. And when one Corinthian being inceſtuous, was not caſt forth, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> prouoketh them all to repentance. Now in our owne declinings we muſt take them betimes, leſt that which is halting turne quite aſide. If a forren enemie inuade vs, wee ſtay not till he come to our gates, but meet him and hold him play betimes. If a bodily diſeaſe breed on vs, we loue to looke forth quickly. Thus it ſhould be, when ſin (an enemy, yea a ſickneſſe to the ſoule) doth ſo much as make entrance into vs. And this is ſure, that often ſmalleſt declinings are not a little dangerous. It is ſeene in nature, that the moſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate diſtemper (ſuch as at firſt is in an hectick fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer) as it is not eaſily found, ſo it is hardly cured. Thus in our ſoules declinings, which wee ſee not to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1240:13"/>be ſo outragious, but that we are well enough for all them, theſe often proue moſt perillous.</p>
            <p>Againe, this muſt moue vs betime to deale with our ſelues in ſinne; for the beginning of it (as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith of ſtrife) is like the opening of waters; lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle though it ſeeme at firſt, yet it will ſwell and riſe till we be ouerflowne with it.</p>
            <p>This therefore muſt checke vs, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> who neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent for the declining of the people in the land, nor the decay of grace in our ſelues. The truth is, that looke as in ſweeping a kennell, the further it is dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen down, the more filth abounds; ſo the lower ages with vs, are as ſinkes receiuing all the defilements of former times, and our iniquities are more encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Now if by repentance we put it not from vs, we make our ſelues little better then actors in preſent tranſgreſſions, by conſenting to them. And for our owne particulars, wee are many of vs to be blamed, who like fooliſh perſons let our fores putrifie, rather then open them, and endure their dreſſing more timely. Many of vs (who till ſharpe fits force vs forth) will not ſeeke out againſt our diſeaſes. Thus eaſe ſlayeth the fooliſh. But let vs be wiſe; let vs not thinke all well, while we can hold vp our head, and feele not the painfull pangs of conſcience. The child is bred, before the pangs of trauell come; ſo the ſin, it may be, hath laine a long time in vs, which if wee in time deale not with, will one day fill vs with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe ſorrowes. A good husband mends a gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; if a tile be fallen, he ſupplieth another; he keepes all winde and water-tite: in like ſort muſt we in theſe ſoules of ours, which are houſes to God his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, we ſhall elſe bring all vpon our heads. And thus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1240:13"/>much for this doctrine, which in the coherence may be obſerued.</p>
            <p>The matter it ſelfe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeru. </seg>5</label> or ſecond exerciſe preſcribed is repentance, ſet downe by the effect of it, <hi>doe thy firſt workes.</hi> Now that againſt this ſicke ſtate he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes this remedie, <hi>Repent;</hi> we ſee what expels and heales all ſuch matters in the ſoule, <hi>viz.</hi> repentance. This will helpe euery malady: were a man ſicke of the conſumption of his lungs, there were ſmal hope, it is <hi>mors lenta,</hi> but <hi>certa;</hi> well, languiſhing Epheſus euen in a ſoule-conſumption is reſtored by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. We ſee in nature euery part hath a faculty of expelling what is noxious and harmfull: the lungs haue their cough; the braine his ſneezing, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excretions; the ſtomacke will turne it ſelfe topſie turuie, but it will bring vp (by vomit) that which offends. Not to proſecute this, in ſtead of all theſe, and ſuch like, the ſoule of man in this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein it contracts corruption, hath this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of repentance put into it, whereby it empties it ſelfe of all that which is offenſiue. But for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther edifying you in this point, I will open two things: firſt, in what this practice ſtands: ſecondly, how we may excite repentance. The act of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is a certaine determination, which the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding makes and propounds. Secondly, in the turning away of the will from that ſinne it lay in; as now hauing it in abomination. Thirdly, in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine affections and actions, which the will (now changed) excites in vs. For firſt, in repentance, the mind apprehends, and determinately ſets downe thus much, that we lie in a fearfull eſtate, guilty of grieuous ſinne; the vnderſtanding ſpeakes theſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1240:14"/>things within vs: O we haue done fooliſhly, what is it we haue done? we are worthy to be cut off; we haue ſinned, done wickedly, peruerſly, Dan. 9. Ezech. 20. Ier. 6.8. 1 King. 8. Now while the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſpeakes this in the ſoule, the will perceiuing by her vnderſtanding, in what euill ſhee hath lien, turnes it ſelfe away, nilling and hauing in abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the ſinne it liued in. What haue I to doe with Idols (ſaith repenting Ephraim), Hoſ. 14? For looke as in the body, not the preſence of ſicke matter, but the ſitrring of it; ſo that nature begins to feele the malignancie of it; this ſtirring is that which makes nature to fight with it, and driue it forth: ſo not the preſence of ſinne, but when the ſenſe of it is conueyed, by this the vnderſtanding ſpeakes, then the ſoules endeauour of turning it away is excited. Thirdly the will thus abhorring it, cauſeth certaine affections to ariſe; as griefe, indignation, reuenge, ſhamefaſtneſſe, 2. Cor. 7. Hebr. 12.28. Yea it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands certaine outward actions; confeſſion, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our ſelues in faſting; ſome, as ſignes and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; ſome, as meanes alſo further helping it. For as after a medecine taken, Phyſitians preſcribe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, ſixe or eight houres more or leſſe, as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things require; and that to this end, that the medecine may more effectually grapple with the matter to be expelled, hauing no auocament: ſo here we reſtraine meates, and all delights for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the fleſh may be more fully wrought vpon by the Spirit; while the worke of the ſoule, by theſe carnall auocaments is nothing hindred. Now for exciting, if hauing ſet before vs our ſinne, we feele not our hearts penitently affected, then muſt we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1240:14"/>thinke how it is with vs in outward euils, and take words to our ſelues, ſaying; Lord, if I ſee any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger towards my body or eſtate, ſorrow will come before I ſend for it. In default but of complement with man, I can be aſhamed quickly: what Atheiſme and hardneſſe of heart is this, that I canthinke of my ſinnes againſt thee, indangering my ſoule, and that without griefe or bluſhing?</p>
            <p>Thus hauing made this diſcouerie of the hard-hartedneſſe in vs, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> we muſt (conſcious of our owne inability) looke to Chriſt, who giueth repentance and pardon of ſinne; who takes away the heart of ſtone, giuing vs hearts tender and fleſhie. If yet it riſe not to our deſire, we need not feare, this is the ſeed which will grow vp to that we wiſh, in due time. This then being thus, that repentance is ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne a medecine for all diſeaſes of the ſoule; how ſhould we be inamoured with it? what good reaſon haue we to hold it in high eſteeme? would not one account much of ſuch a receit, as taken in any bodily ſickneſſe were preſent remedie?</p>
            <p>Againe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> it muſt moue vs to the conſcionable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice here enioyned, ſeeing it is ſo beneficiall to the ſoule: what will we not endure for our bodies? the making them ſicke with bitter potion, inciſion; yea, cutting off, if a member be putrified, ſearing them in diuers parts with hot irons: ſhall we goe thus farre for the good of the body, and refuſe the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this exerciſe for the good of our ſoules? I may ſpeake to thy impenitent breaſt, as <hi>Naamans</hi> ſeruants ſpake to him about the cure of his leproſie: <hi>Father, if the Prophet had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded thee a hard thing, wouldeſt thou not hauedone it? how much more ſeeing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1240:15"/>he ſaith, Waſh and he cleane.</hi> If God had commanded thee a hard thing, wouldeſt thou not haue done it to auoid damnation? How much more muſt thou obey, when he ſaith, Be but grieued, and condemne your ſinnes your ſelues, I will not condemne you?</p>
            <p>Neither muſt they onely, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> who are priuie to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinnes (as more mortall ſickneſſes) repent them; but we alſo, ſeeing we all of vs, though wee haue no ſuch dead ſickneſſes, yet we haue ſuch corruptions as will breed vs bitterneſſe, if we auoide them not by repentance; if ye repent not, you ſhall periſh, ye my diſciples. Men that are well, how would it goe with them, if neither by vrine, nor ſiege they ſhould get eaſement of ſuch ſuperfluitie as it to be expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? they would not long continue well. So it is, though we are well for grace ſhewed vs, yet our ſoule daily contracteth and harboureth ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which if we purge it not forth by renewed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, we may aſſure our ſelues it will turne to ſome fearfull ſoule-ſickneſſe. Let vs not be like ſuch fooliſh ones, who goe on in ſome diſeaſe, rather then they will trouble the humour, and diſeaſe themſelues one day, let things goe on with them till they are cureleſſe. I know the diuell makes it ſeeme a painfull thing to leaue our delights, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet our ſelues, and ſit as Iudges condemning our ſelues within our ſelues. A ſluggard thinkes it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable to riſe; yet when he is vp, he findes it not painfull: ſo here. But were it troublous, is it not better to put thy conſcience out of office, by iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy ſelfe, then haue GOD and thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence condemne thee eternally? To conclude this point, doe we catch any fall bodily, but we will get
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1240:15"/>vp againe, though we riſe from hand to knee, and get vp but faintly? O let vs be wiſe in the fals of our ſoules, take heede to get vp by repentance againe.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the practice of repentance: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeru. </seg>6</label> now for the effect, <hi>doe thy firſt workes,</hi> I obſerue, that ſinne by repentance remoued, our former abilities are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. Euen as in nature, when the actions of any part are hurt by this or that ſicke matter hurting them; take but away the diſeaſe, the part will doe that belongeth to it as ably as euer: ſo the ſoule once healed by repentance, puts forth the powers of it ſelfe as it did before: yea (as they ſay) a bone broken and well ſet againe, is ſtronger then euer it was; ſo Gods often mending the ſoule by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, exceeds the former making of it. This moſt bleſſed exerciſe of a broken ſpirit, who can declare the vertue of it? whether we looke at euils in the ſoule, or in the body and condition. It often hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſoule-euils, ſo that there is no ſcar left in them of the wound receiued. <hi>Peter</hi> a preſumptuous man ſtanding on compariſon, though al theſe leaue thee, yet, &amp;c. <hi>Peter</hi> ſo full of ſelfe-loue, ſo fearfull of death, that he denied his Lord and Maſter: when now God had touched him with repentance, mark how cleere he roſe vp (as it were) from theſe cuils. The night before he ſhould haue been martyred, he ſlept as ſoundly as if he had not been priuie to any ſuch matter: and when Chriſt asked him, <hi>Doeſt thou loue me more then theſe? Peter</hi> now had forgot his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons, <hi>Lord thou knoweſt I loue thee.</hi> So <hi>Dauid,</hi> when God had now enlightened his darkneſſe after the matter of <hi>Vriah,</hi> he felt ſuch ſpirituall ſtrength, as if he could haue leaped ouer a wall, or broken through
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1240:16"/>an armie. True it is that ſomtime when repentance is not in the more through degree, but done by halues; then it is as in bodily diſeaſes, which goe not cleane away, but leaue the party <hi>neutrum conualeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> that is, not well, but onely ſomewhat mending, rather then fully reſtored. This is doth in regard of ſoule-diſeaſes that are entred; but if wee feare their growing on vs, then this practice followed, is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent preſeruatiue, preuenting their entrance.</p>
            <p>Now for bodily and conditionall euils, this keeps them (vſed in kinde) that they befall vs not. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabs</hi> counterfeit repentance obtained no leſſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it makes vs grow out of them, if they haue ſeazed on vs. How did <hi>Iob,</hi> now humbling himſelfe in duſt and aſhes, mount vp (as it were) with Eagles wings, aboue all his clamities? If the ſentence touching outward euils be irreuocablie paſſed, yet ſo it aſſwages and ſweetens theſe croſſes, that wee haue peace in the middeſt of them, and feele not ſo much diſturbance from them. As in <hi>Moſes,</hi> who might not enter Canaan; in <hi>Dauid,</hi> whoſe child was to die, whoſe other calamities threatned, were to ſucceed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> This therefore may ſerue for a touch-ſtone to diſcerne, whether our repentance be right, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: if we haue ſoundly repented, wee ſhall finde it in our freedome from luſts, which ſometime trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled vs in our abilities ſpirituall, and in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of our duties. When by our repentant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation we grow of vngodly, godly; of intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſober; of vniuſt, iuſt; of ſlothfull, feruent in good duties; then we may aſſure our ſelues that our ſinne by repentance is taken from vs. Should wee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1240:16"/>ſee who had been feeble, waſted, now hauing taken phyſicke grow full of blood, fleſhie, able to digeſt any thing, ſtrong to labour; wee would not doubt but that his diſeaſe were fully remoued; but that his medecine was right and effectuall: ſo is that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance right, and that man healed by it, to whom the workes of grace are now returned: but if wee haue not fruits which accompany repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, then is our turning to bee ſuſpected.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 2. line 17. put out <hi>Chriſt.</hi> p. 3. l. 26. for let, r. <hi>viz.</hi> p. 10. l. 22. for meere, r. <hi>new.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
